Finding Aid for Diversity Blueprints Task Force (University of Michigan) records, 2005-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Diversity Blueprints Task Force (University of Michigan) records 2005-2007, 2006-2007
University of Michigan. Diversity Blueprints Task Force.
322 MB
2013042 Bimu
Task Force created by President Mary Sue Coleman in 2006 to help frame the University of Michigan's response to Proposal 2, a state ballot initiative that banned the use of affirmative action and preferential treatment in hiring and admissions decisions. Includes administrative records of the Task Force and its subcommittees in digital format as well as related online resources created by the university. Prominent records include the final report of the Task Force, interim reports of subcommittees, email correspondence, and archived Websites that promoted Task Force findings and diversity in general at the university.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Diversity Blueprints Task Force (donor no. 10930 ) in 2007
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Diversity Blueprints Task Force records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Diversity Blueprints Task Force record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Digital Files
With the passage of Proposal 2 on November 7, 2006, the Michigan State Constitution was amended to ban public institutions from using affirmative action in hiring or admissions decisions or from giving preferential treatment to groups or individuals based on their race, gender, color, ethnicity, or national origin. The University of Michigan responded to this new law by changing its admissions and financial aid policies so that race and gender were no longer factors in the decision making processes. At the same time, the university sought to maintain its vision of education as "a tool through which the fact of diversity is transformed to the exciting and productive actions of diversity, creating a climate and environment so stimulating and attractive that the experience of difference becomes a source of excellence and an instrument of achievement" (University of Michigan Diversity Blueprints Final Report, p. 2). To this end, President Mary Sue Coleman established the Diversity Blueprints Task Force on December 13, 2006 to provide the university with recommendations on how to maintain and enhance diversity on campus in light of Proposal 2's mandate. In its formal charge, the Task Force was asked to evaluate and improve "the University's effectiveness in recruiting, retaining, and supporting a diverse student body, faculty, and staff and enhancing its educational outreach and engagement."
The Diversity Blueprints Task Force was co-chaired by Provost Teresa Sullivan and Senior Vice Provost for Academic Affairs Lester Monts and consisted of 55 faculty, staff, graduate and undergraduate students, alumni, and administrators. This body was divided into four subcommittees, each of which addressed a valued aspect of the university's diverse structure:
Undergraduate Admissions, Financial Aid, and Pipeline
Graduate Student Recruitment, Retention, and Pipeline
Faculty and Staff Hiring and Retention
Educational Outreach and Engagement
The Task Force held five full meetings, four public forums, 35 hours of subcommittee meetings, and a two-day "Workshop on the Impact of Ballot Initiatives and Judicial Decisions on Admissions and Recruitment, Financial Aid, and Outreach" with key administrators from California, Washington, Texas, and Georgia. The task force delivered the University of Michigan Diversity Blueprints Final Report on March 17, 2007 and the recommendations took into account more than 400 suggestions sent via email from students, faculty, staff, alumni, and area residents in addition to numerous comments made in public forums, meetings, and workshops.
The Diversity Blueprints Task Force records will be of value to researchers interested in the University of Michigan's efforts to maintain and enhance the diversity of its campus in response to the limits imposed by the 2006 Michigan ballot initiative, Proposal 2, on the use of affirmative action for admissions decisions. The record group is entirely digital and is comprised of research materials related to other states, statistics and analyses of diversity efforts at the University of Michigan, email correspondence, and reports and recommendations made by the task force and its subcommittees. The record group is comprised of two series: Administrative Files and Archived Websites.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Diversity Blueprints Task Force.; Educational equalization--Michigan; Minorities--Education, Higher--United States.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series is comprised of records created by the Diversity Blueprints Task Force and its subcommittees in the fulfillment of their official charge from President Mary Sue Coleman. The records in this series were originally created and maintained in a collaborative digital workspace (CTools, the University of Michigan's implementation of the open source Sakai platform). Screenshots of this software platform are included alongside records to provide contextual information about the original environment of the materials. The series is divided into six sections: records of the full Task Force, records of the four subcommittees (Undergraduate Admissions, Financial Aid, and Pipeline; Graduate Student Recruitment, Retention, and Pipeline; Faculty and Staff Hiring and Retention; and Educational Outreach and Engagement), and the Task Force final report. The task force and subcommittee records consist of email correspondence (with attachments), report drafts, suggestions from the community, information on diversity initiatives at peer institutions, meeting materials, PowerPoint presentations, and reviews of U-M efforts to promote diversity.
  - Diversity Blueprints Task Force 2006-2007, .ZIP file
    - Email Archive (message attachments include subcommittee reports, event flyers, press releases and other materials)
      [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2027 ]
    - Resources: official charge, recommendations from U-M community, subcommittee presentation slides, U-M Faculty Senate diversity guidelines, and other materials
    - Participant List
  - Educational Outreach and Engagement Subcommittee 2006-2007, .ZIP file
    - Email Archive (message attachments include reports on diversity outreach efforts at U-M and elsewhere, meeting notes, presentation slides, and other materials)
    - Resources: meeting notes, relevant articles and websites, reports on outreach efforts and initiatives at U-M, draft of subcommittee report, and other materials
    - Participant List
  - Faculty and Staff Hiring and Retention Subcommittee 2006-2007, .ZIP file
    - Discussion: includes subcommittee comments on various issues, including 'interdisciplinary,' partner support, and recruitment
    - Email Archive (message attachments include subcommittee work plan, meeting minutes, reports, and subcommittee working papers)
    - Resources: work plan; reports on affirmative action, women's issues, and efforts to increase diversity at U-M; subcommittee recommendations, and other materials
    - Wiki (includes suggestions for possible initiatives related to maintaining faculty and staff diversity)
    - Participant List
  - Graduate Student Recruitment, Retention, and Pipeline Subcommittee 2006-2007, .ZIP file
    - Email Archive (includes a preliminary report on diversity and graduate student recruitment and retention)
    - Resources: draft and final versions of subcommittee report, subcommittee recommendations, and review of peer organizations
    - Wiki (includes draft version of subcommittee report)
    - Participant List
  - Undergraduate Admissions, Financial Aid, and Pipeline Subcommittee 2006-2007, .ZIP file
    - Email Archive (message attachments include draft version of subcommittee report and Stephen M. Ross Academic Center brochure)
    - Resources: meeting agendas, suggestions submitted via email, drafts of subcommittee report, review of peer institutions, and other materials
    - Wiki: multiple discussions related to application process, admissions, financial aid, student retention, program evaluation, and ensuring a diverse pool of applicants
  - University of Michigan Diversity Blueprints Final Report, 2007, .PDF file
- Archived Websites
  The Archived Websites series contains online resources created by the University of Michigan to highlight the Task Force recommendations and general efforts to promote diversity on campus. This series contains archived versions of two different Websites and is arranged chronologically, with content captured by the Internet Archive (from 2005 to 2007) and the Bentley Historical Library (in 2005 and 2007). The archived version of the 'Diversity: Research and Resources' Website presents information and reports compiled by the Diversity Blueprints Task Force and its component subcommittees and includes additional information related to Proposal 2, the Michigan ballot initiative that banned the use of affirmative action in admissions decisions. Archived versions of the 'University of Michigan: The Educational Value of Diversity' Website provide information on landmark legal cases involving affirmative action at the university-- Grutter v. Bollinger (2003) and Gratz v. Bollinger (2003)--and detail efforts and initiatives to promote diversity on campus
  - Diversity: Research and Resources
    - 2005-[ONGOING]
      (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.)
    - June 7, 2007, .ZIP file
  - University of Michigan: The Educational Value of Diversity
    - 2005-[ONGOING]
    - April 18, 2005, .ZIP file
    - March 26, 2007, .ZIP file